(Zhan Zhao Adventures)
(مغامرات زان تشاو)
(Episode 25)
(الحلقة 25)
Our prince was invited by his good friend Bai Yu Tang.
تلقى أميرنا دعوة من صديقه المقرب باي يو تانغ.
He'll attend the event in hopes that he can witness
سيحضر الحدث على أمل أن يتمكن من أن يشهد
a marvelous spectacle about medicine and pharmacology.
مشهد رائع عن الطب وعلم الأدوية.
Prince Hui's presence
حضور الأمير هوي
truly brings honor to our humble home.
إنه حقاً يضفي شرفاً على منزلنا المتواضع.
It's just that we've never hosted such a distinguished guest before.
الأمر ببساطة أننا لم نستضيف ضيفاً بهذه المكانة المرموقة من قبل.
We're afraid of failing to uphold proper decorum in front of royalty.
نخشى أن نفشل في الحفاظ على اللياقة اللائقة أمام العائلة المالكة.
Elder Clan Leader, there's no need to worry.
يا زعيم العشيرة الأكبر، لا داعي للقلق.
His Highness is easygoing by nature.
صاحب السمو يتمتع بطبيعة هادئة.
Your family only needs to host the gathering
كل ما تحتاجه عائلتك هو استضافة التجمع
as splendidly as in previous years.
كما كان الحال في السنوات السابقة، وبروعة مماثلة.
- Alright.   - Yes.
- حسناً. - نعم.
As long as His Highness gets to see his friend at the tournament,
طالما أن سموه سيتمكن من رؤية صديقه في البطولة،
his trip won't have been in vain.
لن تذهب رحلته سدى.
Understood.
مفهوم.
We'll take our leave now.
سنغادر الآن.
You've given me money and even paid for my stay at the inn.
لقد أعطيتني مالاً بل ودفعت ثمن إقامتي في النزل.
You really just want me to tell everyone the truth?
هل تريدني حقاً أن أخبر الجميع بالحقيقة؟
It'll only cost you a couple days' work.
لن يكلفك الأمر سوى بضعة أيام من العمل.
The money is compensation for that.
هذا المال هو تعويض عن ذلك.
But you must repeat before everyone what you told us earlier.
لكن عليك أن تكرر أمام الجميع ما قلته لنا سابقاً.
Alright.
على ما يرام.
That's Yao Yu Shan's house, right?
هذا منزل ياو يو شان، أليس كذلك؟
There's been no word from him for days now.
لم يصدر عنه أي خبر منذ أيام.
He might be dead.
ربما يكون قد مات.
His poor wife is all alone now.
زوجته المسكينة وحيدة تماماً الآن.
Officer Zhan, my master invites you to meet him at Cuixi Forest.
أيها الضابط زان، يدعوك سيدي لمقابلته في غابة كويشي.
This is obviously a trap they set for us.
من الواضح أن هذا فخ نصبوه لنا.
If we really go,
إذا ذهبنا حقاً،
we'll be walking straight into it.
سندخل فيه مباشرة.
Just come up with some excuse.
اختلق أي عذر.
Say there's been a major case in your jurisdiction,
لنفترض أن هناك قضية كبيرة وقعت في نطاق اختصاصك القضائي،
or that you've fallen seriously ill.
أو أنك قد أصبت بمرض خطير.
That stuff about a prince coming in person
ذلك الكلام عن قدوم الأمير شخصياً
is obviously a bluff.
من الواضح أنها مجرد خدعة.
Patience. Let's wait and see.
الصبر. لننتظر ونرى.
Enter.
يدخل.
The plan failed.
فشلت الخطة.
That was within expectations.
كان ذلك ضمن التوقعات.
I'll think of another way to delay the Suwen Tournament,
سأفكر في طريقة أخرى لتأجيل بطولة سوين.
buying you more time to silence them.
يمنحك ذلك المزيد من الوقت لإسكاتهم.
Or perhaps we should simply stop the gathering from happening at all.
أو ربما ينبغي علينا ببساطة منع التجمع من الحدوث على الإطلاق.
No.
لا.
The Suwen Tournament must go on.
يجب أن تستمر بطولة سوين.
And it must be held as scheduled.
ويجب أن يُعقد في موعده المحدد.
On the surface, the board may look like a dead end,
قد تبدو اللوحة للوهلة الأولى وكأنها طريق مسدود،
but sometimes sacrificing a piece
لكن في بعض الأحيان يتم التضحية بجزء
is enough to reveal how many cards your opponent holds
يكفي أن تكشف عدد البطاقات التي يمتلكها خصمك
and uncover a path to survival.
واكتشف طريقًا للبقاء.
So why not?
فلماذا لا؟
Exactly. We should be thanking Zhan Zhao instead.
بالضبط. ينبغي أن نشكر زان تشاو بدلاً من ذلك.
He gathered all the witnesses and evidence for us.
لقد جمع لنا جميع الشهود والأدلة.
Since Officer Zhan wants to lure us into the trap,
بما أن الضابط زان يريد استدراجنا إلى الفخ،
then we'll step right into the game.
ثم سندخل مباشرة في اللعبة.
(Yuelai Inn)
(يولاي إن)
Zhan, Bai is back.
زان، باي قد عاد.
You're here.
أنت هنا.
Madam Jiao and her son have been settled next door.
استقرت السيدة جياو وابنها في المنزل المجاور.
With us guarding them, nothing should go wrong.
بوجودنا لحمايتهم، لن يحدث أي خطأ.
Good.
جيد.
The only key witness left now is Yao Yu Shan.
الشاهد الرئيسي الوحيد المتبقي الآن هو ياو يو شان.
If we can find him,
إذا استطعنا العثور عليه،
our chances of winning will improve greatly.
ستتحسن فرصنا في الفوز بشكل كبير.
But I've been thinking,
لكنني كنت أفكر،
if Luo Wen Jie really is Si Ming,
إذا كان Luo Wen Jie هو حقًا Si Ming
then even with all our witnesses,
ثم حتى مع وجود جميع شهودنا،
he'll still find a way to wriggle out of reopening the case.
سيجد طريقة للتملص من إعادة فتح القضية.
I want to make a trip to Feihua Hollow.
أريد القيام برحلة إلى وادي فييهوا.
- What?   - There'll be heavy rain tonight.
- ماذا؟ - ستكون هناك أمطار غزيرة الليلة.
Qingyu Grass is easy to spot then.
يسهل حينها رصد عشب تشينغيو.
If I really can find the Dawn-Dusk Cocoon mentioned in the notes,
إذا استطعت حقاً العثور على شرنقة الفجر والغسق المذكورة في الملاحظات،
it'll prove my brother really was in the mountains that night.
سيثبت ذلك أن أخي كان بالفعل في الجبال تلك الليلة.
But you're injured. How are you supposed to search for it?
لكنك مصاب. كيف يُفترض بك أن تبحث عنه؟
My brother was pampered his whole life.
لقد كان أخي مدللاً طوال حياته.
He couldn't carry heavy loads or do physical work.
لم يكن يستطيع حمل الأحمال الثقيلة أو القيام بالأعمال البدنية الشاقة.
If he could climb up there,
لو استطاع الصعود إلى هناك،
what's a little injury to me?
وماذا تمثل إصابة بسيطة بالنسبة لي؟
This is the only thing I can do for him.
هذا هو الشيء الوحيد الذي أستطيع فعله من أجله.
But this trip is far too dangerous.
لكن هذه الرحلة خطيرة للغاية.
And even if you find the Dawn-Dusk Cocoon,
وحتى لو عثرت على شرنقة الفجر والغسق،
it still might not be enough to convict Si Ming.
قد لا يكون ذلك كافياً لإدانة سي مينغ.
Be careful.
احرص.
If I'm not back by tomorrow morning,
إذا لم أعد بحلول صباح الغد،
go straight to Qinghui Hall.
اذهب مباشرة إلى قاعة تشينغ هوي.
Don't wait for me.
لا تنتظرني.
Bai...
نعم...
He's still injured.
لا يزال مصاباً.
Let him go.
دعه يذهب.
If he doesn't give it his all tonight,
إذا لم يبذل قصارى جهده الليلة،
he'll regret it for the rest of his life.
سيندم على ذلك طوال حياته.
It's going to rain soon.
ستمطر قريباً.
Let's eat first.
لنأكل أولاً.
Huo, don't worry.
هوو، لا تقلق.
Before the White Rat set off,
قبل أن ينطلق الجرذ الأبيض،
we gave him plenty of mountain-climbing gear.
لقد زودناه بالكثير من معدات تسلق الجبال.
He'll be fine.
سيكون بخير.
Yeah, Huo, the food's getting cold.
أجل يا هوو، الطعام بدأ يبرد.
There's still no sign of Yao Yu Shan.
لا يزال ياو يو شان غائباً عن الأنظار.
You don't think
ألا تعتقد
he's fallen into Si Ming's hands, do you?
لقد وقع في قبضة سي مينغ، أليس كذلك؟
If they force him into giving false testimony...
إذا أجبروه على الإدلاء بشهادة زور...
When we passed by Yao Yu Shan's house today,
عندما مررنا بمنزل ياو يو شان اليوم،
you said something.
لقد قلت شيئاً.
"There's been no word from him for days now.
"لم يصدر منه أي خبر منذ أيام."
He might be dead."
ربما يكون قد مات.
Not that.
ليس هذا.
You said,
أنت قلت،
"His poor wife is all alone now."
"زوجته المسكينة وحيدة تماماً الآن."
Her husband's been missing for days,
زوجها مفقود منذ أيام.
yet she still has the mood to give alms to beggars.
ومع ذلك، لا تزال لديها الرغبة في إعطاء الصدقات للمتسولين.
She knows exactly where Yao Yu Shan is.
إنها تعرف بالضبط أين ياو يو شان.
My husband really hasn't come back.
زوجي لم يعد حقاً.
How would I know where he is?
كيف لي أن أعرف مكانه؟
He's in danger right now.
إنه في خطر الآن.
I truly don't know anything.
أنا حقاً لا أعرف شيئاً.
You should look somewhere else.
يجب أن تبحث في مكان آخر.
If someone else gets to him first,
إذا وصل إليه شخص آخر أولاً،
we'll really have a problem.
سنواجه مشكلة حقيقية.
It's about to rain.
ستمطر قريباً.
It's not appropriate for a man to stay here alone with me.
ليس من اللائق أن يبقى رجل هنا بمفرده معي.
You should leave now.
يجب أن تغادر الآن.
This rain is really coming down hard today.
هذا المطر يهطل بغزارة اليوم.
Huo, is the rain in Xiangzhou always this heavy?
هوو، هل الأمطار في شيانغتشو دائماً بهذه الغزارة؟
It's always like this in autumn.
هكذا يكون الحال دائماً في الخريف.
As for tomorrow's Suwen Tournament,
أما بالنسبة لبطولة سوين غداً،
who knows if our plan will actually work.
من يدري إن كانت خطتنا ستنجح بالفعل.
And I wonder how White Rat's doing.
وأتساءل كيف حال الجرذ الأبيض.
He'll be fine, Huo.
سيكون بخير يا هوو.
His Highness once said,
قال صاحب السمو ذات مرة:
"Heaven looks after good people."
"الجنة تعتني بالناس الطيبين."
No matter how heavy the storm is, it always passes.
مهما اشتدت العاصفة، فإنها تمر دائماً.
Qingyu Grass.
تشينغيو العشب.
It's really the Qingyu Grass!
إنها حقاً عشبة تشينغيو!
Master!
يتقن!
Clan Leader!
زعيم العشيرة!
Master, a group from the prefectural office has arrived outside.
سيدي، لقد وصلت مجموعة من مكتب المحافظة إلى الخارج.
They say the Prefect has come to attend the ceremony.
ويقولون إن المحافظ قد حضر لحضور الحفل.
- Even the Prefect came?   - The Prefect?
- حتى رئيس الطلاب حضر؟ - رئيس الطلاب؟
This year's Suwen Tournament is really something.
بطولة سوين لهذا العام مميزة حقاً.
At last, we'll get to see what this Si Ming really looks like.
وأخيرًا، سنرى كيف يبدو سي مينغ حقًا.
He doesn't seem all that impressive.
لا يبدو أنه مثير للإعجاب إلى هذا الحد.
Look, another carriage is coming.
انظروا، عربة أخرى قادمة.
So grand. Wonder which important figure that is.
يا له من عظمة! أتساءل من هي تلك الشخصية المهمة.
I heard it's Prince Hui.
سمعت أنه الأمير هوي.
Well, he is a prince. Of course he'd arrive in style.
حسناً، إنه أمير. بالطبع سيصل بأناقة.
I'm Luo Wen Jie, Prefect of Xiangzhou.
أنا لو وين جي، مثالي من شيانغتشو.
Welcome,Your Highness.
أهلاً وسهلاً بك يا صاحب السمو.
I'm Zhao Zhi Er, steward of His Highness' estate.
أنا تشاو تشي إر، أمين ممتلكات صاحب السمو.
Greetings, Prefect Luo.
تحية طيبة، أيها المحافظ لو.
Sir, on the way here, His Highness came across some beautiful scenery
سيدي، في طريقه إلى هنا، صادف صاحب السمو بعض المناظر الطبيعية الخلابة
and wished to take a stroll.
وأراد أن يتمشى.
Please head inside first. His Highness will arrive shortly.
يرجى الدخول أولاً. سيصل صاحب السمو بعد قليل.
This way, Prefect Luo.
من هنا يا محافظ لو.
You're number six.
أنت رقم ستة.
The auspicious hour is almost here.
الساعة الميمونة على وشك الوصول.
I'm afraid His Highness won't make it in time.
أخشى أن صاحب السمو لن يصل في الوقت المناسب.
His Highness specifically instructed us
وقد أصدر سموه تعليمات محددة لنا
not to delay the Suwen Tournament on his account.
عدم تأخير بطولة سوين بسببه.
I'll send riders to escort His Highness here at once.
سأرسل فرسانًا لمرافقة صاحب السمو إلى هنا على الفور.
I'm Zhan Zhao of Kaifeng Prefecture, acting under Prince Hui's orders
أنا تشان تشاو من محافظة كايفنغ، وأعمل بأوامر الأمير هوي
to accompany you, Prefect Luo.
لأرافقك يا محافظ لو.
I wouldn't dare. You're an official from the capital.
لن أجرؤ على ذلك. أنت مسؤول من العاصمة.
How could I deserve such treatment?
كيف أستحق مثل هذه المعاملة؟
The auspicious hour has arrived!
لقد حانت الساعة الميمونة!
Prefect Luo,
المحافظ لو،
once the Suwen Tournament begins,
بمجرد بدء بطولة سوين،
all three courtyards will be closed.
سيتم إغلاق جميع الساحات الثلاث.
No one may leave once inside.
لا يُسمح لأحد بالمغادرة بمجرد دخوله.
That rule has stood for a hundred years.
لقد ظل هذا القانون قائماً لمدة مئة عام.
We shouldn't break their traditions.
لا ينبغي لنا أن نكسر تقاليدهم.
Since His Highness won't make it,
بما أن صاحب السمو لن يتمكن من الحضور،
please take the seat of honor in his place.
تفضل بالجلوس في مقعد الشرف مكانه.
Prefect Luo, please.
المحافظ لو، من فضلك.
No, no. That would be far too improper.
لا، لا. سيكون ذلك غير لائق للغاية.
Our prince isn't one for rigid formalities.
أميرنا ليس من النوع الذي يلتزم بالرسميات الصارمة.
Please, Prefect Luo.
من فضلك يا محافظ لو.
Please.
لو سمحت.
I won't refuse then.
لن أرفض إذن.
Prefect Luo, this way.
المحافظ لو، من هنا.
If I'm not mistaken,
إن لم أكن مخطئاً،
His Highness didn't come at all, did he?
لم يأتِ صاحب السمو على الإطلاق، أليس كذلك؟
What are you talking about? Of course he did.
عن ماذا تتحدث؟ بالطبع فعل ذلك.
Huo.
هذا كل شيء.
Even the prince from the Nanqing Palace came to attend today.
حتى أمير قصر نانكينغ حضر اليوم.
I wish I could go outside and see the spectacle for myself.
أتمنى لو أستطيع الخروج ومشاهدة هذا المشهد بنفسي.
Yeah, this year is certainly lively.
نعم، هذا العام حافل بالأحداث بالتأكيد.
Who struck that? It's not time yet.
من ضرب ذلك؟ لم يحن الوقت بعد.
What the hell. We're both right here!
يا إلهي! كلانا هنا!
It's only a few moments early anyway.
إنها مجرد لحظات قليلة قبل الموعد المحدد على أي حال.
If Master finds out we hit the bell early,
إذا اكتشف ماستر أننا ضربنا الجرس مبكراً،
we'll be punished.
سنُعاقب.
Then let me strike it.
دعني أضربها إذن.
Dear friends and honored guests,
أصدقائي الأعزاء وضيوفي الكرام،
thank you all for taking the time to attend the Suwen Tournament.
شكراً لكم جميعاً على تخصيص وقتكم لحضور بطولة سوين.
Jin family is deeply grateful.
عائلة جين ممتنة للغاية.
Especially today,
وخاصة اليوم،
with Prefect Luo honoring us with his presence.
بحضور المحافظ لو الذي شرفنا بحضوره.
His visit brings great glory to our humble home.
إن زيارته تجلب مجداً عظيماً لمنزلنا المتواضع.
Please accept my thanks.
أرجو قبول شكري.
As per the Suwen Tournament's annual tradition,
وفقًا للتقاليد السنوية لبطولة سوين،
each participating disciple holds
يحمل كل تلميذ مشارك
a numbered token.
رمز مرقم.
Matching numbered tokens are also placed inside this box.
يتم وضع الرموز المرقمة المتطابقة أيضًا داخل هذا الصندوق.
When I draw a number, the chosen participant
عندما أسحب رقمًا، يكون المشارك المختار
will step forward for the examination.
سيتقدم للامتحان.
No delays will be permitted.
لن يُسمح بأي تأخير.
Why isn't Bai here yet?
لماذا لم تصل باي بعد؟
He's been gone all night.
لقد غاب طوال الليل.
Whatever herb he was looking for, he should've found it by now.
أياً كان نوع العشبة التي كان يبحث عنها، كان ينبغي أن يجدها الآن.
Number six.
الرقم ستة.
Is number six present?
هل الرقم ستة موجود؟
If not, the slot will be forfeited.
وإلا، سيتم إلغاء الحجز.
He clearly saw that Bai wasn't here and rigged the draw on purpose.
لقد رأى بوضوح أن باي لم يكن موجوداً، فقام بتزوير القرعة عمداً.
I'm number six.
أنا رقم ستة.
Bai Yu Tang asked me to take the test in his place.
طلب مني باي يو تانغ أن أؤدي الاختبار بدلاً منه.
Substituting for someone?
هل تحل محل شخص ما؟
I've never heard of such a thing.
لم أسمع بمثل هذا الشيء من قبل.
How can you take the test for someone else?
كيف يمكنك إجراء الاختبار نيابة عن شخص آخر؟
Everyone, please calm down.
يا جماعة، من فضلكم اهدأوا.
Bai Yu Tang and I did not come here today to compete.
لم نأت أنا وباي يو تانغ إلى هنا اليوم للمنافسة.
With Prefect Luo present,
بحضور المحافظ لو،
we wish to take this opportunity
نود أن ننتهز هذه الفرصة
to appeal to him regarding a wrongful conviction from years ago.
لتقديم التماس إليه بشأن إدانة خاطئة صدرت قبل سنوات.
If you have a grievance, take it to the yamen.
إذا كانت لديك شكوى، فاعرضها على مجلس الشعب.
This is not a courtroom.
هذا ليس قاعة محكمة.
No office in Xiangzhou dares to accept this case.
لا يجرؤ أي مكتب في شيانغتشو على قبول هذه القضية.
Because this case
لأن هذه القضية
was personally closed by you years ago, Prefect Luo.
تم إغلاقها شخصياً من قبلك منذ سنوات، أيها المحافظ لو.
So Jin family, this is why you invited me here?
إذن يا عائلة جين، لهذا السبب دعوتموني إلى هنا؟
You... y-you... Hand that over here!
أنت... أنت... أعطني هذا هنا!
The moment Master agreed to let Little Seventeenth compete,
لحظة موافقة ماستر على السماح للفرقة الصغيرة السابعة عشرة بالمشاركة،
I knew I had to stay on guard.
كنت أعلم أنه يجب عليّ أن أبقى متيقظاً.
Where's Little Seventeenth?
أين ليتل سيفينتينث؟
Where's that brat?
أين ذلك الطفل المزعج؟
Get out here!
اخرج من هنا!
You're an outsider.
أنت غريب عن المكان.
What right do you have to meddle in Jin family's affairs?
ما هو حقك في التدخل في شؤون عائلة جين؟
This isn't just the Jin family's business.
هذا ليس مجرد عمل لعائلة جين.
Bai Yu Tang's brother
شقيق باي يو تانغ
was Jin Xue Wen, eldest son of the fifth branch
كان جين شيو وين الابن الأكبر للفرع الخامس
of the Jin family's thirteenth generation.
من الجيل الثالث عشر لعائلة جين.
He was accused of murdering a young woman.
اتُهم بقتل امرأة شابة.
Everyone here has at least heard of that case, right?
جميعنا هنا سمعنا على الأقل بتلك القضية، أليس كذلك؟
And the victim was my aunt.
وكانت الضحية عمتي.
So how exactly do I not have the right to seek justice here?
فكيف لا يحق لي السعي لتحقيق العدالة هنا؟
- You...   - Everyone,
- أنتم... - الجميع،
my aunt died under suspicious circumstances.
توفيت عمتي في ظروف غامضة.
The real killer has remained free all these years,
لقد ظل القاتل الحقيقي طليقاً طوال هذه السنوات،
while Jin Xue Wen carried the stigma for 15 years,
بينما تحملت جين شيو وين وصمة العار لمدة 15 عامًا،
even being cast out of the family registry.
حتى أنهم طُردوا من سجل العائلة.
Today, I ask Prefect Luo
اليوم، أسأل المحافظ لو
to retry this case before everyone present
إعادة محاكمة هذه القضية أمام جميع الحاضرين
and give them justice.
وأعطهم حقهم.
Right and wrong,
الصواب والخطأ،
good and evil,
الخير والشر،
everyone here will bear witness.
سيشهد الجميع هنا على ذلك.
Elder Clan Leader,
زعيم العشيرة الأكبر سناً،
allowing her to make such a scene here,
السماح لها بإثارة مثل هذه الضجة هنا،
what kind of decorum is that?
أي نوع من اللياقة هذا؟
If this is the sort of behavior you permit,
إذا كان هذا هو نوع السلوك الذي تسمح به،
perhaps the Suwen Tournament
ربما بطولة سوين
shouldn't be held at all.
لا ينبغي عقدها على الإطلاق.
Please don't be mad, Prefect Luo.
أرجوك لا تغضب يا محافظ لو.
Young lady,
يا آنسة،
if you truly have a grievance,
إذا كان لديك شكوى حقيقية،
please wait until after the tournament.
يرجى الانتظار حتى انتهاء البطولة.
Prefect Luo will hear your case then.
سيستمع المحافظ لو إلى قضيتك حينها.
All these people came to witness the event,
جاء كل هؤلاء الناس ليشهدوا الحدث،
not to sit through a trial.
عدم حضور المحاكمة.
Elder Clan Leader, judging by seniority,
زعيم العشيرة الأكبر سناً، استناداً إلى أقدميته،
you would be Jin Xue Wen's great-uncle.
ستكون عمّ جين شيو وين الأكبر.
A member of your family has been wrongfully convicted for over a decade.
لقد أدين أحد أفراد عائلتك ظلماً لأكثر من عقد من الزمان.
Is that less important than a tournament?
هل هذا أقل أهمية من البطولة؟
I heard that while he was alive,
سمعت أنه أثناء حياته،
Jin Xue Wen respected you deeply.
كان جين شيو وين يكن لك احتراماً عميقاً.
And now, with his name still uncleared,
والآن، مع بقاء اسمه غير واضح،
you can still sit here
لا يزال بإمكانك الجلوس هنا
hosting the Suwen Tournament as if nothing happened?
استضافة بطولة سوين كما لو لم يحدث شيء؟
Well said, young lady.
أحسنتِ يا آنسة.
A healer needs more than medical skill,
يحتاج المعالج إلى أكثر من مجرد مهارة طبية،
they must also possess compassion.
يجب أن يتحلوا أيضاً بالتعاطف.
If the wronged person is one of our own in the medical community,
إذا كان الشخص المتضرر أحد أفراد مجتمعنا الطبي،
how can we ignore his injustice
كيف لنا أن نتجاهل ظلمه؟
and continue chasing fame and prestige here?
وهل نستمر في مطاردة الشهرة والمكانة هنا؟
I believe the competition can wait.
أعتقد أن المنافسة يمكن أن تنتظر.
Hearing this young lady's appeal is the most important thing right now.
إن الاستماع إلى نداء هذه الشابة هو أهم شيء في الوقت الراهن.
Well said! Well said!
أحسنت! أحسنت!
Retry the case! Retry the case!
أعد المحاولة! أعد المحاولة!
Surely Prefect Luo wouldn't ignore the grievances of the common people?
بالتأكيد لن يتجاهل المحافظ لو شكاوى عامة الناس؟
Please, have a seat, Prefect.
تفضل بالجلوس يا رئيس.
Or perhaps I could help you gather a few more men
أو ربما أستطيع مساعدتك في جمع المزيد من الرجال
to shout "court is in session" or something.
أن يصيح قائلاً "المحكمة منعقدة" أو ما شابه ذلك.
I work for the prefectural office.
أعمل في مكتب المحافظة.
I'm constantly traveling between the various county yamen.
أنا أسافر باستمرار بين مختلف المدن التابعة للمقاطعة.
Do you think Prefect Luo will retry the case?
هل تعتقد أن المحافظ لو سيعيد محاكمة القضية؟
State your grievance now.
عبّر عن شكواك الآن.
However,
لكن،
it's a case from 15 years ago.
إنها قضية تعود إلى 15 عاماً مضت.
I may not remember it clearly.
قد لا أتذكر ذلك بوضوح.
Prefect Luo.
المحافظ لو.
The case files and evidence from back then are all here.
جميع ملفات القضية والأدلة من ذلك الوقت موجودة هنا.
If you can't remember clearly,
إذا لم تستطع التذكر بوضوح،
perhaps reviewing them will refresh it.
ربما مراجعتها ستنعشها.
How did you obtain these case files?
كيف حصلت على ملفات هذه القضية؟
This case was concluded by Xiangyang County back then.
وقد تم إغلاق هذه القضية من قبل مقاطعة شيانغيانغ آنذاك.
Naturally, the files were retrieved from the Xiangyang County yamen.
وبطبيعة الحال، تم استرجاع الملفات من مكتب مقاطعة شيانغيانغ.
The county deputy and registrar said
قال نائب المقاطعة ومسجلها
that the archives storeroom caught fire two days ago,
أن مخزن الأرشيف اشتعلت فيه النيران قبل يومين،
and all the records and files were burned to ashes.
وتم حرق جميع السجلات والملفات حتى تحولت إلى رماد.
Luckily, I transferred these files out beforehand.
لحسن الحظ، قمت بنقل هذه الملفات مسبقًا.
If you don't believe me, you can verify it.
إذا لم تصدقني، يمكنك التحقق من ذلك.
That won't be necessary.
لن يكون ذلك ضرورياً.
According to the case file,
بحسب ملف القضية،
Jin Xue Wen was convicted as the murderer
أُدين جين شيو وين بتهمة القتل
based on three witnesses and two pieces of physical evidence.
استناداً إلى ثلاثة شهود واثنين من الأدلة المادية.
The first witness was the steward of the Jin residence.
كان الشاهد الأول هو مدير منزل عائلة جين.
Xu An.
شو آن.
Mr. Xu, please step forward.
السيد شو، تفضل بالتقدم للأمام.
Xu An,
شو آن,
come forward and speak.
تقدم وتحدث.
Yes, sir.
نعم سيدي.
Back then, you claimed you saw Jin Xue Wen
في ذلك الوقت، زعمت أنك رأيت جين شيو وين
harassing the victim before the murder,
مضايقة الضحية قبل القتل،
that he was speaking frivolously and getting handsy.
أنه كان يتحدث باستخفاف ويتحرش بالآخرين.
Think carefully.
فكر جيداً.
What exactly did he say,
ماذا قال بالضبط؟
and how exactly did he touch her?
وكيف لمسها بالضبط؟
What else could he say?
ماذا عساه أن يقول أيضاً؟
Whenever he saw that girl, he'd chase after her
كان يلاحق تلك الفتاة كلما رآها
calling her "beauty that could sink kingdoms,"
وصفوها بأنها "جمال قادر على إغراق الممالك".
comparing her to heavenly goddesses.
تشبيهها بالآلهة السماوية.
He praised her like she was some celestial maiden from the moon palace.
أثنى عليها كما لو كانت عذراء سماوية من قصر القمر.
When the girl ignored him,
عندما تجاهلته الفتاة،
he'd reach out
كان يمد يده
right there in public and touch her hair.
هناك في مكان عام ولمس شعرها.
And after touching it, he'd hold it up to his nose and sniff it.
وبعد لمسه، كان يرفعه إلى أنفه ويشمه.
Is that something a decent man would do?
هل هذا شيء يفعله رجل محترم؟
Yeah.
نعم.
Doesn't that sound a little familiar?
ألا يبدو ذلك مألوفاً بعض الشيء؟
Not just to me,
ليس الأمر مقتصراً عليّ فقط،
doesn't it sound familiar to all of you too?
ألا يبدو هذا مألوفاً لكم جميعاً أيضاً؟
Yeah. Over these past ten days,
نعم. خلال الأيام العشرة الماضية،
coming and going from the Jin Residence,
الدخول والخروج من مقر إقامة جين،
I've heard the exact same story at least three times.
لقد سمعت نفس القصة بالضبط ثلاث مرات على الأقل.
Of course,
بالطبع،
each time you told it, Jin Xue Wen was harassing a different girl.
في كل مرة كنت تروي فيها القصة، كان جين شيو وين يضايق فتاة مختلفة.
I'm sure the rest of you have heard it even more often than I have.
أنا متأكد من أنكم سمعتموها أكثر مني.
But Jin Xue Wen was a gifted scholar.
لكن جين شيو وين كان عالماً موهوباً.
Even if he were to use lewd words,
حتى لو استخدم كلمات بذيئة،
wouldn't he be more creative than that?
ألن يكون أكثر إبداعاً من ذلك؟
He wouldn't say the exact same thing to every woman.
لن يقول نفس الكلام بالضبط لكل امرأة.
When it comes to harassing women,
عندما يتعلق الأمر بمضايقة النساء،
the words are pretty much the same. How different can they be?
الكلمات متشابهة إلى حد كبير. ما مدى اختلافها؟
The insults you've been hurling at us these past few days,
الإهانات التي كنت توجهها إلينا خلال الأيام القليلة الماضية،
have they all been word-for-word identical too?
هل كانت جميعها متطابقة كلمة بكلمة أيضاً؟
Which is why I have reason to suspect
ولهذا السبب لدي سبب للشك
that you heard Jin Xue Wen say something like that to some girl one day,
أنك سمعت جين شيو وين يقول شيئًا كهذا لفتاة ما في يوم من الأيام،
and you just memorized it.
وقد حفظتها عن ظهر قلب.
After that, no matter which story you were telling,
بعد ذلك، بغض النظر عن القصة التي كنت ترويها،
you reused the same account.
لقد استخدمت نفس الحساب مرة أخرى.
- I...   - Can testimony like that really be trusted?
- أنا... - هل يمكن الوثوق بشهادة كهذه حقاً؟
No!
لا!
It can't be trusted!
لا يمكن الوثوق به!
I'm not lying!
أنا لا أكذب!
You're not lying?
أنت لا تكذب؟
Then repeat exactly what Jin Xue Wen said
ثم كرر بالضبط ما قاله جين شيو وين
when he harassed the victim!
عندما قام بمضايقة الضحية!
Yeah! Go on! Say it!
أجل! هيا! قلها!
Come on! Repeat it!
هيا! كررها!
I'm old. I can't remember clearly.
أنا كبير في السن. لا أستطيع التذكر بوضوح.
Is it that you can't remember,
هل المشكلة أنك لا تستطيع التذكر؟
or that you never actually heard it?
أم أنك لم تسمعها في الواقع؟
Is it that you just saw Jin Xue Wen talking to the victim
هل رأيت للتو جين شيو وين يتحدث إلى الضحية؟
and assumed he was harassing her?
وافترضت أنه كان يضايقها؟
Xu An's testimony was based on hearsay.
استندت شهادة شو آن إلى أقوال منقولة.
Even if most of it cannot be taken as fact,
حتى وإن لم يكن بالإمكان اعتبار معظمها حقيقة،
Jin Xue Wen's reputation for being lecherous and frivolous
سمعة جين شيو وين بأنها فاسقة وسطحية
was common knowledge.
كان ذلك معروفاً للجميع.
Is that not enough?
أليس هذا كافياً؟
Since you put it that way,
بما أنك طرحت الأمر بهذه الطريقة،
then that means Xu An's testimony is officially invalid.
إذن هذا يعني أن شهادة شو آن غير صالحة رسمياً.
Luo Wen Jie really is an incompetent fool.
لوه وين جيه أحمق غير كفؤ حقاً.
If it weren't for all your help over the years,
لولا كل مساعدتكم على مر السنين،
he'd have been dead many times over.
لكان قد مات مرات عديدة.
The second witness in the case was the current head of the Tang Sect,
وكان الشاهد الثاني في القضية هو الرئيس الحالي لطائفة تانغ.
Tang Ji.
تانغ جي.
In court,
في المحكمة،
Jin Xue Wen claimed that on the night of the murder,
زعمت جين شيو وين أنه في ليلة الجريمة،
he went to Feihua Hollow, 40 li outside Xiangyang, to gather herbs.
ذهب إلى وادي فييهوا، على بعد 40 لي خارج شيانغيانغ، لجمع الأعشاب.
Before entering the mountain,
قبل دخول الجبل،
he ran into Tang Ji and a woman
صادف تانغ جي وامرأة
at Chunxin Pavilion at the mouth of the valley,
في جناح تشونكسين عند مدخل الوادي،
and exchanged greetings with them.
وتبادلنا التحية معهم.
But Tang Ji denied it outright in court.
لكن تانغ جي نفى ذلك بشكل قاطع في المحكمة.
Tang Ji isn't present today.
تانغ جي غير موجود اليوم.
So how do you intend to refute his testimony?
فكيف تنوي دحض شهادته؟
It's true I can't refute it.
صحيح، لا أستطيع دحض ذلك.
But someone else can prove Jin Xue Wen wasn't lying.
لكن بإمكان شخص آخر إثبات أن جين شيو وين لم تكن تكذب.
Who are you?
من أنت؟
Sir,
سيد،
my name is Cui Tian. I'm from Jiang Village.
اسمي كوي تيان. أنا من قرية جيانغ.
I make a living as a hunter.
أعيش من مهنة الصيد.
Every summer and autumn, I stay in Feihua Hollow for a few months.
في كل صيف وخريف، أقيم في وادي فيهوا لبضعة أشهر.
20 years ago,
قبل 20 عاماً،
I often saw a man and a woman
كثيراً ما كنت أرى رجلاً وامرأة
meeting secretly at Chunxin Pavilion.
الاجتماع سراً في جناح تشونكسين.
15 years ago, even when the plague was at its worst,
قبل 15 عاماً، حتى عندما كان الطاعون في أسوأ حالاته،
they still met in the mountains regularly.
كانوا لا يزالون يلتقون في الجبال بانتظام.
I remember it clearly.
أتذكر ذلك بوضوح.
Do you recognize Tang Ji?
هل تعرف تانغ جي؟
No.
لا.
But I've seen his portrait.
لكنني رأيت صورته.
The man in it looks extremely similar to the one I saw back then.
الرجل الذي يظهر فيه يشبه إلى حد كبير الرجل الذي رأيته في ذلك الوقت.
A portrait?
صورة شخصية؟
And you think a portrait alone is enough to confirm that man was Tang Ji?
وهل تعتقد أن صورة واحدة تكفي لتأكيد أن ذلك الرجل هو تانغ جي؟
Officer Zhan,
الضابط زان،
you certainly weren't this lenient
بالتأكيد لم تكن متساهلاً إلى هذا الحد
when questioning Xu An just now.
أثناء استجواب شو آن الآن.
Whether the hunter can identify Tang Ji isn't important.
لا يهم ما إذا كان الصياد يستطيع التعرف على تانغ جي أم لا.
What matters is that his testimony proves Jin Xue Wen was not the killer.
المهم هو أن شهادته تثبت أن جين شيو وين لم يكن القاتل.
On the night of the murder, he wasn't in the city.
في ليلة الجريمة، لم يكن موجوداً في المدينة.
He was in Feihua Hollow.
كان في وادي فيوا.
That's why he saw a man and woman meeting secretly at Chunxin Pavilion.
ولهذا السبب رأى رجلاً وامرأة يلتقيان سراً في جناح تشونكسين.
The hunter also said just now
وقال الصياد أيضاً الآن
that this man and woman met in Feihua Hollow every year.
أن هذا الرجل والمرأة كانا يلتقيان في وادي فييهوا كل عام.
Maybe Jin Xue Wen saw them years before the murder.
ربما رآهم جين شيو وين قبل سنوات من وقوع الجريمة.
He could've lied and claimed he saw them on the night of the crime itself.
كان بإمكانه أن يكذب ويدعي أنه رآهم ليلة وقوع الجريمة نفسها.
That's also possible, isn't it?
هذا ممكن أيضاً، أليس كذلك؟
Wouldn't that make him incredibly stupid?
ألن يجعله ذلك غبياً للغاية؟
He insisted he spoke to the man,
وأصر على أنه تحدث إلى الرجل،
and repeatedly claimed that man was Tang Ji.
وادعى مراراً وتكراراً أن ذلك الرجل هو تانغ جي.
If it were a lie,
لو كان ذلك كذباً،
wouldn't he just be waiting for you
ألن يكون بانتظارك؟
to find Tang Ji and expose him on the spot?
للعثور على تانغ جي وفضحه في الحال؟
Prefect Luo,
المحافظ لو،
there are also many inconsistencies in the evidence from back then.
كما توجد العديد من التناقضات في الأدلة من ذلك الوقت.
The case file states that the tears on this bloodstained robe
يذكر ملف القضية أن التمزقات الموجودة على هذا الرداء الملطخ بالدماء
were caused by my aunt scratching him.
كانت هذه الإصابات ناجمة عن قيام عمتي بخدشه.
But the wounds on Jin Xue Wen's shoulder were over an inch deep.
لكن الجروح على كتف جين شيو وين كانت أعمق من بوصة.
Could human fingernails cause that?
هل يمكن أن تتسبب أظافر الإنسان في ذلك؟
Then in your opinion,
ثم برأيك،
how were those wounds caused?
كيف حدثت تلك الجروح؟
I am Jin Xue Wen's younger brother.
أنا الأخ الأصغر لجين شيو وين.
Let me tell you
دعني أخبرك
how my brother got those injuries.
كيف أصيب أخي بتلك الإصابات.
Back then,
في ذلك الوقت،
the coroner made this sketch based on the wounds on Jin Xue Wen's body.
قام الطبيب الشرعي برسم هذا المخطط بناءً على الجروح الموجودة على جسد جين شيو وين.
The proportions,
النسب،
the size,
الحجم،
and even the depth of the wounds
وحتى عمق الجروح
are identical to the injuries on Bai Yu Tang.
وهي مطابقة للإصابات التي لحقت بـ باي يو تانغ.
They really are identical.
إنهما متطابقان تماماً.
Something's not right here.
هناك خطب ما هنا.
Back in court,
العودة إلى المحكمة،
my brother said he had gone into the mountains that night to gather herbs.
قال أخي إنه ذهب إلى الجبال تلك الليلة لجمع الأعشاب.
He wasn't lying.
لم يكن يكذب.
The herb he sought grew beside a cave where hawks nested.
كان العشب الذي يبحث عنه ينمو بجوار كهف تعشش فيه الصقور.
The wounds on his body were caused by a hawk attacking him.
كانت الجروح التي لحقت بجسده ناجمة عن هجوم صقر عليه.
When that hawk returned with food
عندما عاد ذلك الصقر بالطعام
and saw me at the cave entrance,
ورآني عند مدخل الكهف،
it thought I meant harm to its eggs,
ظنت أنني أنوي إيذاء بيضها،
so it attacked me viciously.
لذا هاجمني بشراسة.
My brother must've gone through the exact same thing back then.
لا بد أن أخي قد مر بنفس التجربة تماماً في ذلك الوقت.
That's why the wounds were so similar.
ولهذا السبب كانت الجروح متشابهة للغاية.
And I've found the herb he went to gather.
وقد وجدت العشبة التي ذهب ليجمعها.
The Dawn-Dusk Cocoon.
شرنقة الفجر والغسق.
Surely the Jin family head and Elder Clan Leader recognize this?
من المؤكد أن رئيس عائلة جين وزعيم العشيرة الأكبر يدركان ذلك؟
Before it hatches, it's completely translucent and burns hot as fire.
قبل أن يفقس، يكون شفافاً تماماً ويحترق بشدة كالنار.
Yes, this is the Dawn-Dusk Cocoon.
نعم، هذه هي شرنقة الفجر والغسق.
You actually found such a rare treasure.
لقد عثرت بالفعل على كنز نادر للغاية.
In the well of the old house on Huaihua Alley,
في بئر المنزل القديم في زقاق هوايهوا،
I found the Dawn-Dusk Cocoon my brother collected back then.
لقد وجدت شرنقة الفجر والغسق التي جمعها أخي في ذلك الوقت.
15 years ago, first place should have been his.
قبل 15 عاماً، كان ينبغي أن يكون المركز الأول من نصيبه.
You claim this thing is a Dawn-Dusk Cocoon?
هل تزعم أن هذا الشيء عبارة عن شرنقة الفجر والغسق؟
Fine.
بخير.
Even if this pile of mush really is one,
حتى لو كانت هذه الكومة من العجين بالفعل واحدة،
how do explain someone saw him leaving the victim's house that night?
كيف يمكن تفسير أن شخصًا ما رآه يغادر منزل الضحية في تلك الليلة؟
Are you referring to Madam Jiao, Prefect Luo?
هل تقصد السيدة جياو، المحافظة لو؟
Please let us through.
أرجو السماح لنا بالمرور.
I gave false testimony back then.
لقد أدليت بشهادة زور في ذلك الوقت.
The person I saw that night was not Jin Xue Wen.
الشخص الذي رأيته تلك الليلة لم يكن جين شيو وين.
The man who came out of that courtyard was my husband,
الرجل الذي خرج من تلك الساحة كان زوجي،
Jiao Chao Gui, master of Shengyun Manor.
جياو تشاو غوي، سيد قصر شينغيون.
What did you say?
ماذا قلت؟
Jiao Chao Gui personally confessed to me
اعترف لي جياو تشاو غوي شخصياً
that he had severely wounded Lady Huo.
أنه أصاب السيدة هو بجروح بالغة.
He also told me to lie to the authorities
كما طلب مني أن أكذب على السلطات
and frame Jin Xue Wen.
وإطار جين شيو وين.
He threatened to kill me if I disobeyed him.
هددني بالقتل إذا عصيته.
I swear to heaven
أقسم بالله
that if a single word of this is false,
أنه إذا كانت كلمة واحدة من هذا الكلام خاطئة،
may the entire Jiao family be wiped out.
أتمنى أن تُباد عائلة جياو بأكملها.
I can't believe that happened.
لا أصدق أن ذلك قد حدث.
Then Jin Xue Wen was truly wronged.
إذن، لقد تعرض جين شيو وين للظلم حقاً.
You treacherous woman!
يا لكِ من امرأة خائنة!
How dare you give false testimony!
كيف تجرؤ على الإدلاء بشهادة زور!
You deceived me and protected the killer,
لقد خدعتني وحميت القاتل،
causing an innocent man to suffer injustice for 15 years
تسبب في معاناة رجل بريء من الظلم لمدة 15 عامًا
and die with a bitter grudge.
ويموتون وهم يحملون ضغينة مريرة.
Guards!
حراس!
- Seize her!   - Yes, sir!
- اقبض عليها! - حاضر سيدي!
Prefect Luo, why are you suddenly acting so outraged?
يا محافظ لو، لماذا تتصرف فجأة بهذه الغضب الشديد؟
Madam Jiao certainly bears blame,
السيدة جياو تتحمل اللوم بالتأكيد،
but the one who closed the case back then was you, not her.
لكن الشخص الذي أغلق القضية آنذاك كان أنت، وليس هي.
You're right.
أنت على حق.
It was precisely because she deceived me
كان ذلك تحديداً لأنها خدعتني
that I convicted the wrong man.
أنني أدينت الرجل الخطأ.
I've failed the Imperial Court
لقد فشلت في المحكمة الإمبراطورية
and failed the people.
وخذلت الشعب.
This case was riddled with inconsistencies from the start,
كانت هذه القضية مليئة بالتناقضات منذ البداية،
yet you convicted a man based solely on
ومع ذلك فقد أدنت رجلاً بناءً على ذلك فقط
a few witnesses' one-sided statements,
بعض التصريحات الأحادية الجانب من الشهود،
completely ignoring all the contradictions.
متجاهلاً تماماً كل التناقضات.
Prefect Luo,
المحافظ لو،
were you truly deceived into making a wrong judgement,
هل تم خداعك حقاً لإصدار حكم خاطئ؟
or did you conspire with the real killer
أم أنك تآمرت مع القاتل الحقيقي؟
to set Jin Xue Wen up as the scapegoat?
لجعل جين شيو وين كبش فداء؟
How dare you slander me in public!
كيف تجرؤ على تشويه سمعتي أمام الملأ!
The crime scene was covered in sword marks.
كان مسرح الجريمة مغطى بآثار السيوف.
Who replaced the furniture to conceal them?
من الذي استبدل الأثاث لإخفائها؟
And why was there not a mention of those sword marks in the case files?
ولماذا لم يُذكر وجود آثار السيوف تلك في ملفات القضية؟
What sword marks? I remember nothing of the sort.
ما هي آثار السيوف؟ لا أتذكر شيئاً من هذا القبيل.
You don't remember?
ألا تتذكر؟
Someone else does!
شخص آخر يفعل ذلك!
Prefect Luo,
المحافظ لو،
do you remember him?
هل تتذكره؟
15 years ago, when you were still the Xiangyang magistrate,
قبل 15 عامًا، عندما كنت لا تزال قاضيًا في شيانغيانغ،
he and Wang Xing were constables under you.
كان هو ووانغ شينغ شرطيين تحت إمرتك.
My name is Yao Yu Shan.
اسمي ياو يو شان.
Greetings, Prefect Luo.
تحية طيبة، أيها المحافظ لو.
Yao Yu Shan.
ياو يو شان.
How long were you planning to hide?
كم من الوقت كنت تخطط للاختباء؟
Officer Zhan,
الضابط زان،
how did you recognize me?
كيف تعرفت علي؟
The second time I went to your house,
في المرة الثانية التي ذهبت فيها إلى منزلك،
I noticed your wife wasn't nearly as anxious.
لاحظت أن زوجتك لم تكن قلقة بنفس القدر.
I should've realized then that she knew where you were.
كان ينبغي عليّ أن أدرك حينها أنها كانت تعرف مكانك.
And beggars usually beg in crowded marketplaces.
وعادةً ما يتسول المتسولون في الأسواق المزدحمة.
But you and the others always stayed in the back alleys,
لكنك أنت والآخرون كنتم تبقون دائماً في الأزقة الخلفية،
never leaving even in the rain.
لا يغادر أبداً حتى في المطر.
So I guessed someone must've been bringing you food every day.
لذا خمنت أن أحدهم كان يحضر لك الطعام كل يوم.
Just now, I recognized you
لقد تعرفت عليك الآن.
because you weren't quite like the other beggars.
لأنك لم تكن مثل المتسولين الآخرين تماماً.